Now, we've called the order, the regular meeting of the Maris City Council for Monday, October 4, 2021.
Two public input and unscheduled personal preferences, we have one, this route, Stevens.
Everybody has a hand out that she gave.
Thank you, everybody.
Is this, is it a picture?
Oops, sorry.
You can pull it down.
You have your code of ordinance in front of you, the Section 23417.
That's why I'm here.
I live at Route 66 landing.
My son brought me here from Tucson four years ago, and it was wonderful.
I live on the fifth floor.
I have 20 windows.
That is the most beautiful apartment you can ever imagine.
In Tucson, it would rent for 2000 a month.
And we should really be proud of it.
But since we've had the street Route 66 fixed,
the noise is, it's horrible.
We can't sleep.
It's all night long.
And it's mufflers.
Now, I know there's all the excuses, all the catalytic converters are being stolen, all that.
No, this is on purpose.
And when I had my dogs, I would walk this street at night,
and they would love to come up right beside me and give a big pop.
It sounded like a gunshot.
And scared us to death, and they would just laugh and just so funny.
I'm really, I have to sign my lease now for the next year,
and I question if I even want to live here.
Because you don't own mainstream, any longer.
It's not yours.
It has been totally taken over by RIPRA.
And we want three things.
We want a sign that says quiet zone.
Second thing.
A speed limit sign.
And then third, enforcement.
And we have 24 apartments in that building.
Some of the residents are over 90 years old.
I'm 83 by the way, getting there.
And one lady even had to hurt a lady, just they'm pitated.
And we can't rest.
We can't sleep.
It's all night long.
And we keep calling the police department.
I've talked with Chief Anderson.
Today I talk with the Indians.
I don't know where else to go.
Don't know what else to do.
I think.
What we are are thinking of doing the residents is standing out there in our night gowns,
holding signs, having photos taken, and I'll send them to every newspaper and Oklahoma so
that they know what's happening in my air, and I hate that I love historic gowns, but it's
totally wiped out from all of this reference. And they love it. And we've set out there
as not kids. It's 20 and 30 year olds. We had an officer out to see us last Sunday, and
he was very nice Brad Mullin, I believe it was, but he's on leave now. He's there giving birth
to a little girl. And he said, well, if it will help, we'll set down here, but of course,
he's not there anymore. So what can we do? What do you say? It's a hopeless situation, and
it's too bad because the apartments are beautiful. And we have a good social life there,
we have the jam, we have the community room, we have the pool room, we have the puzzle room, but I'm
sorry. You can't live with that kind of racket all the time, and they love it. They just love
to do it. So we could start with the three things I mentioned, the quiet zone. They used
to have quiet zone signs there, I've heard that. What happened? We can't even carry conversations
to bad because it's a beautiful building.
So I'm leaving it there and we do have ladies believe it or not who are ready to go
We're going to go out and our nidies with our signs saying we can't sleep be quiet
One lady in a wheelchair went out one night and shook her finger at him
And of course they probably really enjoyed that because they think it's also funny
I went I know you probably it don't like my my shit show, but I went on that one
Just to see what the feeling was and one of the responses was well, we don't do drugs and we work
So we should be privileged in order to do this and so of course my
Response was I've worked 63 years and they'm retired. What's my privilege? I don't have a privilege
I don't have to sleep apparently
But it's it's just too bad. It's really a let down that
That this town would let that happen and main street isn't yours. I would said just I've been president of the
Visitors bureau in another town and I would hate to hear statements like this
Because who wants to come and walk down the historic
Streets of the town if you have to walk in the alleys or the side streets because you can't walk on the main street because it's so noisy
I don't know how people even cross the street because there's no lights of course anymore
But we've sat down there and watched them. They will stop at the four-way stop on first street and then gun the motors
Try to get us a ties they can until they get to central in one block and that's how they make the noise
So
That's all I have to say
Just leave it with you guys, but but you will be getting some advertisement before you go to advertising
Is there a time in the evening?
It would seem
Agreeable to have those activities
Start to come to the hall
They usually start
The big time around seven thirty and then
It just increases in momentum and then it
It goes on to one and two o'clock
And you've never know when it's gonna stop and then the next morning at seven thirty it usually starts in the morning
And then it will ease off to noon and then again at nine at seven thirty. I mean
We it's like cock work. We know when it's gonna happen, but there's no way to get away from it
Not at all so I did more than my question correctly
Would there if boys we're gonna be boys from 7.32 what every time you get ready to tell me here in just a second
What would that magic time be that you would like it to get quiet if they were gonna be silly for a couple hours or whatever
If you thought through that at all
Well, how late to how you're asking how late can that can the big boys be little boys, right?
But yes, face it out of you. Yes, man
Well, in the evenings we're watching
TV and we're watching football games trying to then we go to bed
Yeah
But it is very difficult even now see even on Saturdays
They can this and if you're watching football it's a lot of us are football fans
It and I literally feel at times that my head is a based drum and it's like this and
And it is affecting me. I know we were joking earlier that were like this
But but that's really how I'd hit you after a while it just wears on you until you start yelling at different about different things that have nothing to do with that
It's just your reaction
Who want it does
so
That dip was supposed to be there permanently
It was part of the construction process right now
Well, we've labeled at the night of the living dead because that's
You know, it's it's horrible and
Also, it ends all right
And the three consent agenda staff recommends we approve items 4 through 7.
So, I'm going to thank you.
Hi.
Eight.
Approved or reject the Grand Gateway Pell event outside organizational contract for a fiscal year 21.
22.
I'm just going to give you a little bit of a penalty information a minute.
But then I talked about just an opportunity to get front of you guys.
It's been a while because of COVID.
But I just want to explain one time really what Green Gateway is.
We're a co-op of local governments.
The city's in county's created us like 55 years ago.
And so we're theoretically year-end boys.
I think the Attorney General made that really about 40 years ago.
And we can contract and do things because the council government is just good boys.
And so we've been.
We do a lot of things.
We do rule-firing.
You know, less than you know I've met.
They were not economic development activities because, you know, I've been around.
I've been at Green Gateway 29 years.
So I've been here for a long time.
I actually, when good rich clothes, I was a grad student.
It came down here to research on trying to figure out what we're going to do with a good rich clothes.
And that's where we came up with the Perky Park.
And we came up with the office park.
And you know, we've just done a lot of projects.
And I was here for progress parks development.
And those couple of things.
And that's the economic development community on the side of us.
We also do a rule-firing advance.
We fund the area agencies on AG with help and legislature.
And, you know, so we do a lot of things at Green Gateway.
But we're really yours.
You guys own us.
We work for you.
And I just wanted to make that clear.
Now we are a full profit entity.
But we are.
Is we're trying to provide this federal grant to you for Pellan.
That's cheap as we can do it.
Because we know that your match is what matches our federal grant.
Now theoretically, it's a 50-50 percent operating grant.
But the truth is, in my image case, you pay about 10 percent of the way.
And we're scrounging together those other dollars to keep that match down.
I think we supplied some numbers to you.
It's a little over 400,000 more costs for the city service.
We've also added the tribes.
We sell advertising on the buses.
And we do everything that we can to try to keep those costs down as a service to you.
And I think there's sometimes a little bit of confusion about this.
And I think there's a question about how we do extra hour things.
And theoretically, we're licensed by the grant to do from 7.30 to 4.30.
And we've been able to extend hours and use contracts that we have with the tribes.
We've done some other things.
We've chased some other grants.
And we've some things that we've just picked as we tried it.
We've done some other things.
in the service without adding additional cost.
And one of the things that we've tried to do throughout the years is meet your quest.
And I've done it with the Chamber of Commerce and Leadership by Ameth.
But it's against the law for us to what they call a charter service, robotic charter service.
And so every time we ask for that permission, we get Jefferson, lines, and greyhound
and people kind of complain and we don't get to what we're not allowed to do that.
So our really our only choice is to do those extra things, is get them in our grant early and make it a route that's served once a year.
We do that with KMO and Benita.
We've done projects like that here with you.
And so other than that, we are just trying to break you.
So when you ask for something a little special, whether you end up using your shun up, we're putting
in extra buses out there, we'll pay an extra drivers and we're just trying to cover the service.
We get no profit.
There is no profit and penalty.
And what we do is you're in applying the match a few years ago with a different council.
There's a lot of questions about how we are giving discounted rods to natives.
And what we actually did is we got a grant from them and they actually paid the freight on each rod.
Each rod of ours is booked.
It's audited from the federal and state government.
We do it every day.
And so we don't really have any extra money.
I think we provided to Ben the budget for the Miami Out program.
And you put about $46,000 and a little over $400,000 for the project.
And so those things, we are trying to keep your cost as low as we possibly can.
Now, we operate this in like seven cities.
And you are our truly our biggest system.
We provide more service here in Miami than we do in, I would say, a WASO in KMO combined.
And this is a crisis.
It's a first one.
You're the first entity that joined the year old first city.
It's a joint great gateway.
They're also the first contract that we ever signed with.
Peleband was here in Miami.
So what we've been able to do is use that federal grant that they give us.
And but we've expanded it throughout the years and that's why it's no longer 50-50 match.
Because the grant hasn't increased.
The service has.
And part of that service.
I used to come to you guys probably every two or three years when we had two or three bands in town.
And we was felt like we could safely haul about 33 people a day.
And when it got beyond that, we started seeing accident.
It's a bit used to be my attorney.
And he said, we would have little accidents.
And so that's when we'd come to the city and say, you know, we're getting beyond our safety limits.
And you guys want to add a bus.
And this would be the extra cost for it.
And recently, we actually added the tribal operation here.
We partnered with ITC and those tribes.
We've not had that kind of growth.
We've been able to supply after our services.
We've done different things with them.
But we're just running it for you.
This grant rather than coming to the city and mine for you to operate.
We operate on behalf of the seven counties in our area.
And so, that's why we do it.
But I will literally literally eat cities
a separate operation.
We find the answer that way, we show every ride.
And so, that will actually, that $500 will be glad to do it,
but if it's worth the wallet,
we're just going to add it to your cost.
And that, because we don't have,
we don't make money.
There's no more grant money available.
And we're just really providing, really,
a four million-dollar system, you know,
regional-wide, what should be a two million-dollar operating
two million from then.
And we've got it down to like $50,500,000 with a grant,
and the cities come up with the other thing.
So, every time we sell a wrap,
it's the little, your cross-tiered Miami,
we have the cost to Miami, just for Miami.
We don't blend the system.
So, we make the city of Miami stand alone,
we make the need of stand alone,
like gross stand alone, we want to play more stand alone.
We even were asked to do a while,
so a few years ago, because they're half of the while,
so it was in our counties.
And so, that's how we run that system.
The same is true with prior.
But so, that's, so when you see our costs,
it's our actual costs.
And we spent days with your attorney, not being with another one.
We came over and looked at our books and made sure
that we were not unfairly given the need of your eyes
that weren't being paid for.
And so, I'm glad to come and talk to you.
I know Jill serves on my board.
She's heard all this stuff before and how we were structured.
But that's how we do it.
And I just wanted to explain that to you,
that I was going to let Kendrick get up,
and she really runs the program,
and explain to you what's happening to your ridership,
and where we're going, and we're trying to try to come up
while I'm in the hole, and we guys like to hear from Kendrick
and then explain to you how you're going to do it.
Hello, I'm Kendrick, and I'm the Director of Pelvian Transit,
and Ed is absolutely right.
We get a $46,000 match from you guys
and the operation costs us about $400,000 to around.
But that's okay, because this is what we do.
But I do want to explain to you that that contract
is specifically for seven, three to four very service.
We're happy to do anything extra,
but we do have to kind of talk about that
because what we're doing is we're pulling away
from your service and we're getting into charter regulations,
which could get Pelvian into big trouble.
But I want to talk about your numbers right now,
since I think that a lot of you have
and heard the Pelvian's feel before,
you do have one of the most innovative public transit systems
in the state in the nation.
Actually, you have the most efficient innovative in the state,
hands down.
We have implemented an after-hour service
to your system called pick transportation,
which is a partnership with Uber.
So you actually have a public drop-down that runs from five to 10
and 10 to two on Saturdays.
It takes care of that and financially through the grants.
So that's one of the things that you have going.
But my aim is a very, very transit-dependent area.
For example, your numbers in 2019,
for your 46 for the maps that you guys pay,
for 2019, we gave 29,719 trips.
Now, in 2020, we dropped down to 18,400
and that was with COVID-19.
Your numbers actually stayed the highest throughout our system,
and currently, right now.
Right now you're at 11,000 and six trips and we still have months and months to go.
So Miami is a very transit dependent area and as far as pick transportation goes we've been
rolling this project out your after hours transportation project which comes at no cost to
the city.
You have currently since June 1st we've given 218 trips in that system.
That doesn't sound like a lot but it really is and it's very cool.
We've also transported 12 wheelchair dependent individuals which means that we've given
them freedom to move about the community of Miami after hours.
I'm seeing that most of your trips are being used for shopping which means that we contribute
to the local economy in a big way as well.
But I wanted you just to kind of know where your numbers are out with the system to see
that you're steadily increasing to let you know that we're happy to do any kind of extra service
that we have.
I think that next time maybe I should sit down and communicate that with someone from the
city that might be a good move we're happy to do those things we just have to be really careful
of charter regulations and just wanted to make sure that you know that the system that we provide
to you is very efficient and it's a pretty good deal.
So does anyone have any questions for me?
Yeah.
I wish I should have brought pick folders for you guys.
I did not do that but I've got to come to Miami in the next couple of weeks.
So I'm going to bring them down so you guys can take a look at some of that as well with
the after hour system.
But yeah, any questions that you guys have were happy to help?
What's your name?
Oh yeah.
In our mileage at our ridership is audited every year.
We have a very innovative, we're very technologically advanced.
We have one of the most advanced rural systems in the nation by far.
So all of our trips are booked that way so we can easily get you print out that I usually
get those to you once a year but I can start giving you numbers.
Maybe come to a council meeting once a quarter or something like that and kind of talk to you
about where we are with things.
That would be a help I'm happy to do that.
Yes.
Thank you.
And I love my I'm because you're the very first I've only been there five years, but I feel like I've been there a lot longer
So but yeah, this was the first city that signed a contract for a real transit in this area. So thank you
You're mad at hangar on talking to me. I don't remember
Well, that's exactly
Thank you
So looking for a approval reject most of the proof
All right
Nine the approval reject the ODL health
Literacy contract between the Oklahoma Department of Libraries and the my I'm a public library in the mountain $9,000
An authorized the city manager to sign
Just to make that clear their the contract is for grant with the Department of Libraries
we started that
2014 we were saved $3,000 and
We've been doing this over the years. I think there was one year that we didn't
One year that we didn't have it but we mostly done gardening and exercise classes and cooking classes
We've got some other things as well
We have six
Garden beds at Ottawa County Health Department. You can still see those if you drive by we put in three at the boys and girls club
And then
One at the lead agency we've had Tai Chi classes yoga classes
Even chair exercise classes for seniors and then we've had a multitude of cooking classes
A lot of them have been for kids mostly through the boys and girls club. We've gone to Miami
We've gone to commerce. We've gone to Fairland and
And you can see the
The lovely the mayor's lovely daughter Jordan over at the left because she's taught a lot of these classes
She's a
Nutritionist at northeastern tribal health system and then also we've had
classes for adults as well. And so this is just a kind of review up to you today and then
Kelly's going to tell you a couple things about the current brand.
So last year we got this brand and if you're a curve ball because of COVID and we had to kind
of think out of the outside of the box on it. So last year we did a lot of virtual programming.
So this year we're excited because we get to step into in-person again. So what I have planned
I've got several fitness classes lined up with Bible arm, white knife, Rick police going to do
Tai Chi with us again and then Kelsey Weiner is going to do some aerobics classes. We're going to have
classes for kids and adults. We're going to be doing cooking classes for children and adults. Some
at the boys and girls clubs, some at the library. With that I actually found two chefs out of
Tulsa that are willing to travel up here and do those classes for us. So they'll be able to do some
actual professional style cooking as well as tie in the healthy aspect of eating fruits and vegetables and
how to prepare those. We're also going to have some informational classes. One of the things we struggle with
in this community is just healthy eating and activity. So the health department's going to come in and talk
about diabetes. They're going to talk about proper nutrition. We're going to do some teen health
classes with them as well. So here's some of the partners that we work with last year. We did the
farmers market. I don't know if anybody saw that out there. We handed out smoothie kits. We taught people
how to make healthful smoothies with fresh ingredients and then we pass those out for them to make it home.
So this year it's going to be a little bit different. We're going to just advertise that the farmers
market. I could say the health department's going to help us out. And we're going to be trying to
help boys and girls club and integrists are all part of this great. It may not be a big grant, but it
can do big things for a community. Thank you. So move. Second. Two. Please step a second.
10. Approve or approval or rejection of preliminary design and implementation of natural learning environment
outdoor classroom project. This is something that we're very excited about. We always hope that
the life just comes to us and very seldom does it ever work this way all the way through.
Late last year, early this year, I think it actually started with Amanda and Bo, who's out of medium
and we were approached by the tribes about putting in a natural outdoor classroom at some location.
So after discussion, settled on the flashback,
that's about there to kind of explain that complex.
Nothing that I have done very little on this project.
This is really a tribally run project.
Diana Baker with the Shawnee Tribe, Carol Essex,
with the Ottawa Tribe, and Tracy Beck with Miami Tribe.
They're a really spearhead in this project.
They can't just vary into the ones that want to go.
Those aren't want to play anymore.
So we just really got to kind of set that.
We're bringing it to you.
We're happy.
So we're happy.
We're asking if you're afraid we'll switch you away from it.
They want to keep this all natural.
With just dirt, stones, mulch,
through the ground spot you see on there.
Actually elevated six to eight left heels.
And they'll have hides, walk, drop-wall,
and things like that, fill in two of those.
So they really listen to us when we talk about maintenance.
So they can't everything really stone and mulch
that try to keep everything natural.
You always send them to the park and really have them.
You can see they can have them out for a farm.
Helps tides, flash pad into this outdoor land.
You can bring the building to you.
You can always send them to the park and visit the park.
You need to call protection underneath that bridge.
Because we're part of that.
Everything else is just enough.
With that being a ground field side,
we had to be very careful about what we did on the ground.
So we sent them to the room, soil, management plan from BDQ.
And they worked with that.
And that's why everything's coming up.
That was going back.
You see the rope, the rope, the rope, the rope, and it's open to the public.
It's a great part of that, it is.
Anybody can use it?
They put no regulations on us on the use of Jews or anything on it.
That all back together, one of the place where everybody can use it, that's what they decide.
This is their landscape that they give us some distinction between the classroom and the splash.
That's the same as the splash pad, just in the south.
It really lift that whole north side open for an amphitheater or anything else we want to do on that whole.
When we talk about something, this is a 300 to 300 75,000 dollar project.
This is not something that we could have done on our own.
So we're talking about partnership and tribes.
This is really the first one that is kind of a book of water to see how this works.
They have a lot of great ideas that may be able to help us out the future parts.
This is just kind of the first one.
And this is only three tribes get involved.
So that is not a brand new to us.
We don't have anything like this in town.
I volunteer Tyler for a lot of stuff.
As far as lighting and things like that.
There is a really like this up.
This may have to move a little bit when we're in another pod or something.
And we also talked a little bit about video.
Security is only a concern everywhere we go.
So that's definitely something we've looked at.
Harder is already new.
or stage an area on side, on the east side, the parking lot.
So hopefully we can match the parking lot
in this flashback on the west side.
Any questions?
They wanted to be here tonight,
but all three of them sent me any mail today
that something else came up.
So how long do they think this will take?
Time-widening, talking to you, you've got to ask
you to go to a concerned about weather,
not just building up to work all of you all.
If you get time-widened, we'll find out.
We'll find a lot.
It's curtain rocks.
Did you get that over there?
Yeah.
Come on.
The playground equipment.
Time-wideners?
Yes.
Don't get it.
The T-set, yeah.
No, the T-set, the grand, the marches.
It's on the mulch.
Is it like natural mulch or is it natural?
It's not the rubber.
It's not the same thing.
It's not the same as natural.
It's what I want to do with wooden mulch, or something.
They're lighting.
But once the natural was possible, how do you make the poles look like trees, please?
That's it.
That'd be really nice.
If you look at the letter, the tent that's in your packet,
they're going to have some additional funding for the next couple of years
to help kind of offset the maintenance of this,
and maybe add additional things to do this.
After 2023, it becomes off.
The city is fully responsible for it.
It's going to become our so-it's back.
But after 2023, we'll have to see what kind of project
you make.
So, I'm assuming parks will be maintaining it.
Or today.
Now, how is that going to be with employees and staff and time?
No, obviously.
That's the thing that scares us more than anything.
I wish you weren't staffed as it is, just because we can't be hired.
I can do that we've advocated.
We need to help with the development.
We needed to go there.
We no longer have the ability to pull them and use them
for something else.
So that isn't concerned.
That's always the inside.
We will.
We'll make it happen.
We will not get a little bit of thought about your style.
So, exactly where we were proving today
or rejecting just the design.
Just to design.
implementations.
I think it's good to me.
I think it's great.
I'm actually excited to see it.
Start going.
We're just a bunch of guys up here.
I'm concerned about the design.
It's a...
It looks great.
I think it is really, really good job on this.
There's been a lot of time.
When we first started this project,
it was really rushed.
It was here guys.
It's a great time to try and use.
They let that roll off.
It's a traditional grandma.
So they slow down.
So they really took the time.
But the thought is,
we have to use them a couple of different times.
They really listen to us on length.
It's part of the time.
They're cornered round.
They didn't think it's not that good.
So, Marsha,
have somebody who's done some outdoor things like this.
What are your thoughts?
Maybe not to this scale.
But you've done smaller projects like this.
You said they'd have additional funds for the next couple of years.
Is that just for maintenance or was it...
Wouldn't it be an opportunity to expand it?
Well, it's for maintenance and with the ability to add additional features.
If they see necessary reasons.
How's our from a public safety perspective do you see any issues with this?
But we were talking to an amphitheater. You're off the talk of the walking trail that would go around
Let me make a motion. We have proved
Hi, thank you
11 except a reject contract with Ottawa County Sheriff's Office and Sheriff David Damien's here tonight. Thank you for coming
We are
It should be right on
We're very excited about this the project
We've been trying to get off the ground for several years and just a day where we did take off this
We were really able to put forward and currently are just by center
In fact
In Sheriff's Office this patch is for their agency some people go through them for
One-and-a-kind stuff and I know it's always been to combine that
We're currently working on this kind of first step in that big plan
When we read it, our dispatch center
Last year we re-designed it made it capable of pulling extra staff and putting it in third center
The third control we pulled more staff
This year, we walked on the action of the process and said hey we're building a BGFC
We're going to put secure location in there. We don't have a
We're dispensing a platform
We're going to build a storm and we're going to do a BGFC
So they're building this facility so we'll lose this after you
We'll have one county one dispatch center all the way about 15 staff
They've pitched in funds
All of those have about 15 dispatchers currently have
They're going to have two
A lot of tribe partners who have
Stayed in their business
Bloods might not just for additional staff
So if you find it, have three people on staff
24.7 and this is going to put in safety for all of them.
You know, why is all dispatcher one told me that dispatcher
is safe seconds, second safe lives?
This is going to save minutes.
It's just, it's a great thing for public safety and
you can buy it in dispatcher and you don't hear coming
shut up, sorry.
Is anyone having that?
Any other questions on it?
Basically, we'll bring in dispatches over
in the past.
The city will treat people to add to our staff and then we're going to take
the work for baseball.
Are there things to dispatch at your students?
No, they're moving over here.
Are there two dispatches?
This is going to give you some time.
They'll be coming up.
Then that's all.
Then we'll have to move out there.
Then the whole thing will move out there.
At least that.
Yes.
They've talked a long time ago when we saw a man, right now talking about
new furniture, new radio equipment, totally decked out, we've talked about
leaving a radio pump up here and for a backup center if we needed, but
they'll have a branded facility with new equipment and really be able to provide better
services for everybody.
They're still sitting in the middle of the place and they'll just be working
outside.
We have several employees who've been with city for quite some time and they're
bussing the retirement, they're about a bit and as far as the package, city has the
best employee package to their new city employees and just work to a different one page.
But this and they'll be right here that you've ran through just a couple of minutes.
They'll create two new activities that they're funded by the Charity Un.
So, that was really, that's for two people, that's really, three thousand.
That was just to get you.
Yeah.
You know, in guys I would just have to say, this is something that, um,
the chief and the sheriff absolutely need to be commended on for starting this for this is something
that's been talked about for a long time.
Prior to this, this overall agreement that we're talking about, the city has been dispatching
for 23 organizations for years, without any compensation, really, and nothing significant.
That's been the burden of the city, but what they're doing today and starting on this path is completely
changing that culture in the group that they have.
We've met now, I don't know, three or four times.
The culture of that room is just phenomenal.
We've got counties, tribes, city, other cities, municipalities, all involved in that group,
which is involved, first responders, coming together and everybody is committed
to creating this shared service environment, because they know we can do more of a blast
of the whole resource.
Stop everybody spending individually and trying to manage everything, every aspect of it on their own.
And the collaboration in that room is phenomenal, the commitment that's coming out of that room is phenomenal.
And I have no doubt.
Yes.
Absolutely.
This is absolutely the first step.
And I think everybody should know, this is really kind of a monumental moment.
We have, I'll give examples of the benefit of this.
And there's a house fire pitcher, an episode out there.
We can't wait to not want such a work that's calling to church in town.
Church is heading called Auto County.
Auto Kansas, we know this by fire, so it's not my own.
By the time I am on this batch out, there's 13 minutes of these people sitting and watching it have a burn.
That's in turn.
Where they could have called one call, we could have had this batch.
Probably 10 minutes off that.
We're not sure if we want to provide answers.
We're all here.
And one thing with this, I'm wondering, when you, next other day, I'll have it on the board of campus visitors.
They'll agree.
And then there's some logistics that I have to figure out.
So you're looking to make it two weeks and I'll keep it two weeks.
So what does that do with our employee count on the work?
I mean, we are limit our cap.
It's raising the cap.
That's what we're going to work.
But really, since the city's paying for work is really raise our cap.
I mean, the county.
They'll be sitting in police, so it will raise our overall count by two.
So we have ready their cap to get in.
Say that again.
Do what?
I don't think we're ready to say it.
We didn't approve it.
We talked about it.
We never did do it.
So I guess we didn't fair that out.
We'll call it two weeks.
Right?
We overall budgeted cap by two positions.
Which was guaranteed by the funding coming from Chris.
It's just over all that.
I don't think it's defined and it hasn't been stored.
I think it's just an overall head count.
Great, Jim.
That means we're probably going to come back and do that cap again if we are.
We're ultimately going to get in place.
Right.
We're going to be right now.
We have a table of training.
Once we get these two in training.
So it'll be several months down the road before we add the other three.
And work up those in the user's planning.
So right now we do need.
We will have to have to.
I'll make the motion we approve.
And increase the complete cap by two.
Second.
I'll work.
All right.
Thank you.
I don't think yes.
12.
Mayor's nomination to the point Rich Slyllard to the mom of downtown
Redevelopment Authority in DRA replacing Debbie East.
Turnemooks by our eight twenty nine twenty four.
Motion.
Second.
Hi.
All right.
13.
Another new business of any of those.
Business of the busing of this agenda.
14.
Staff reports.
15.
Mayor and council community announcements.
The weather's going to be great.
And if you are a softball fan.
Lift up behind the high school.
Thursday at noon.
Hopefully again Thursday at six.
And probably afternoon at two.
Those are the games.
We stay on the winter side of the bracket.
And that's to be optimistic.
The girls have worked really really hard.
They're they're coached up.
They're ready.
Um.
There's a trip to state laying in the balance and we appreciate your sport. Those girls love a pack of cows and lots of noise
Let's give it to
16 mayors or city managers
You know the only thing that I had that I really wanted to mention night and unfortunately the sheriff left but was to really
again
Point out what Chief Anderson and Sheriff Dean not only beyond what they've been talking about with this this kind of one
Center, but
Collectively
Watching that relationship between the sheriff's office and the city
I can't tell you it is a goal tremendously just in the last number of months
The collaboration between the two organizations working with the tribes
We've had multiple
Opportunities to be collaborating with tribes talking about across digitization and all the paperwork
I'm going to use the documents that they've got to get pulled together that are not only protecting our officers
All the officers that are out there servicing this community
I just a lot goes to those guys in what how they set that to me
And I think there are many many many more great things to come, but the collaboration has just been tremendous
Unfortunately the sheriff left before I got to say those words, so please pass on to him to Chief
It just means a lot in these are things that Chief had brought to me when I first came on and he said here's here's some things
We've been working on for years and years and years and they have all seemed to be coming together
And it's because everybody's pulling together and working together and that I mean tribes counties other cities
We've just been really awesome
Thank you in the sheriff for all you've done Chief also in
Info and info
Once again, don't you have a new position you might mention it's pretty impressive
Awesome, that just says a lot about the caliber of individuals that she is and the leader that she is in this state
So Val, thank you for all of your thank you for all of your
I know how I'm going to step back for a minute because I forgot to say one of my
Robby coach
fire department, and graduated him on his 25 years with my
fire department, so that's not him, that's cheap, but, but, but, but
anyway, I sit and rob you our congratulations, that's, that's
quite a feat, 25 years, so we appreciate you service.
All right, 17, adjournment.